welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
okay we're gonna begin
welcome to the stoah I'm Peter Lindbergh
the steward of the stoah and for those
of you who are coming for the first time
the stoah is a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the nice edge of this moment I am NOT
viewing it as a place just to practice
and talk about stoicism while that will
surely happen here but a place for us to
talk with non stoic Stoics alike and
practice all sorts of different psychic
technologies around this digital
campfire today we have Zack Stein with
us
Zack is a philosopher of Education
working at the interface of psychology
and metaphysics and politics and he's
are currently an associate at
perspectiva and you recently wrote an
article that was on the emerge platform
called kovat 19 a war broke out in
heaven and it was really well written
you gotta got some good buzz on the
sense-making web and it's mostly about
tracking human development so I'll hand
it to Zack in a moment he'll share his
thoughts maybe talk about the article
and then we'll open it up for Q&A and
how the Q&A will work if you have you
know a warm up Zack with some questions
and if you have any questions just write
it in the chat box and I will call on
you unmute you and then just ask your
question to Zack if you'd like me to
read your question on your behalf just
indicate that in the chat box as well so
that being said I will hand it over to
you Zack
thank you Peter yeah it's wonderful to
see all the faces on the camera I've
been doing a lot of just dyadic and
triatic
conversations so this is actually
quite wonderful to have such a large
group and to be talking to Stoics is
also nice for me yeah you have to kind
of even get into what we're gonna be
talking about I've been a caregiver for
various sick people in my life and the
first time I had to do that Marcus
Aurelius and some of the other Stoics
were key in helping me kind of bring
over my Buddhism and get it in touch
with my understanding of Western
philosophy and also in just reminding me
about the agency of tragedy and human
complexity and that is kind of a species
specific trait it is the grappling in
the reckoning with tragedy and so I
think the stoic philosophy is one of
those that can accommodate tragedy and
transcend tragedy without denying
tragedy which is exactly what has to
have them now that Marcus Aurelius is in
his diet that we are completely
interconnected to all things in the
universe doesn't mean that the things
right up next to us don't matter it just
means that we can put them in
perspective so that we can deal with
them in an appropriate way and so a lot
of what I'm hearing from spiritual
circles
is not correct
you know the denial of tragedy the
denial of objective reality is part of
the problem right now not part of the
solution and so what we want to bring
people up and out of getting stuck in
the tragic and being incapacitated and
overwhelmed by the situation we want to
do that we want to liberate people from
their shallower concerns and from their
neurotic preoccupations that are making
their suffering worse we want to do that
but we don't want to say things that
deny the tragedy of the actual situation
so and this is why I accepted to come to
a meeting of Stoics because suffering
pain these things are part of the stoic
philosophy and also a kind of non
escapist transcendence if I can put it
that way and a non escapist
transcendence if it's it to be to be
fully in the world but not of it which
is to say to act as an independent cause
and not only as the result of the
cousins causes and conditions that put
you there right so this notion of
freedom and fate right and destiny these
are all part of the stoic lexicon so I'm
happy to be here that's about where I'll
leave it you know what I said in the
paper is what I wanted to say at this
moment about it and my sense is that you
know there's so much more to be said
right now I'm in very close
communication and working and
collaborating with people like Danish
Magdeburg and Jordan Hall we trying to
put boots on the ground trying to
actually do things trying to do sense
making in different areas about the
infrastructure and a whole bunch of
topics which you've heard Jordan speak
about at length and so I'm not speaking
into those domains I'm trying to speak
into the domains of the human and
especially into the kind of imminent
mental health crisis for lack of a
better term that's coming but exactly
right so that's my urgency is there like
we need masks in the hospital and we
need economic stimulus packages and we
need a whole bunch of things than the
kind of lower right-hand quadrant if you
will they're in but we also need a
tremendous number of innovations in the
realms of psycho technology and in the
realms of took quote for baekje and in
the realms of practice and ritual symbol
so I welcome any questions in those
areas even though I have things to say
about what's happening that's not what
I'm
to speak about him here to speak to the
heart and to the thoughts of the heart
mm-hmm so I will warm up Zach with a few
questions if you have any questions for
Zach again put it in the chat box and
I'll call on you and you on mute you if
you want me to read in your pass just
let me know in the chat box there was a
piece that you or a line that you said
in the article we are living in the
liminal a time of pure potential and
change a time between worlds and I feel
this and it's like I can't really
remember it was like when it dawned on
me this was gonna be a big deal a couple
weeks ago I couldn't really just
cognitively process this this shutdown
really I just kind of handed the keys to
the what I call the Dame on that certain
quality of intuition that says go here
and then this project emerged and then
once I started to kind of we had like
about 20 events within 10 days and I'm
starting to see this as sort of like a
an incubator for cycle technology I'm
just inviting a lot of people just to
test stuff because you know the zoom is
a different framework and everything and
certain things are starting to emerge
like we have the existential dance party
we have like stoic breath like a wim HOF
thing so it's like it's really cool and
it feels it feels like alive so just a
general question I guess personally for
me and maybe for the rest of the people
who are regulars here at the stoah is
any advice on how to go about this kind
of psycho tech testing well I mean one
one first thing is to think about the
frames and think about the metaphors and
so I think the psychological technology
is a good metaphor but it's actually not
my preferred metaphor because it's a
technology right and so I like to think
about practice and ritual as such and
technology is in the lower right so zoom
is the technology in a sense it's a new
aspheric technology right it's about
transmission of ideas and the internet
and all of that so I see that as realms
of technology which are in play but the
things we're looking for are the things
we do with our bodies and with our
voices which are actually deeply organic
and so I'm actually looking for
a return to the you know a return to the
ritual of living together this is what
we're asked to do in one sense and so
it's in I'm not against technology but I
am against the idea that the human being
works like a piece of technology or that
the mind works like a piece of
technology so so that's one of my first
things okay is it really a technology or
is it for example something like a
natural process right that is actually
like a rediscovering right of an organic
reality and always already exist in
reality within the living body of the
human within the bones and the DNA is
the possibility for the forms of
consciousness that we are getting when
we dance right or when we hold each
other with the proper language so I'm
looking for a certain kind of deepening
into the always already present
capacities of the human organism that
are there and so meditation is one of
the classic ones but dialogue oh this is
another and then many of the rituals
which we've inherited from the great
traditions could be re potentiated and
so I'm thinking along those lines as
well but when it comes to figuring out
what works for a group or what works for
oneself then were in a delicate
situation of self clarification and
basically having communities of practice
right because the key thing at least for
me and I think many Stokes would agree
is not the subjective experience one has
when doing a practice it is the way that
practice conditions your choice right is
the way the impact of that practice on
your choice making its effect on others
let's say so
if it makes you feel good that's
wonderful I'm not saying that's bad but
I am saying that the the payload to
delivery what we're looking for at the
end of the day is a is a right action is
the condition for the possibility of
right action and sometimes that will
actually require going deeper into for
example the pain that someone else is
experiencing right in order to say the
right thing to this person I need to
understand their interior state more I
need to understand their pain more right
that's intense it's a lot to ask but as
a caregiver with a sick person you have
to do that at times like if you're a
parent for a child you have to
understand what they're feeling in order
to say the right thing and so and this
isn't this is an ability that humans
have to care for one another
I think it's another species specific
trait right like other animals don't
take care of their sick right humans
take care of the sick it's interesting
like from a strictly Darwinian
perspective like that's a bad idea
like if the universe runs the way Darwin
said or Darwin in quotation marks to
kind of like fiction of Darwin that
we've created because Darwin was
actually much more complex but if it
runs that David Attenborough kind of
stereotypical Darwinian way then we
shouldn't be taking care of the sec
right but we do right there's a implicit
in the human and the being of us is a
generosity and then Anna Karenina ghin
deepening empathy and doing the
practices not necessarily that make you
feel good although we need that and
often these do make you feel good so I'm
there it's not mutually exclusive at all
but the practices that allow you to to
do the right thing to be the person you
need to be to say what needs to be said
and so that's about clarifying who you
are clarifying the realities in the
field of your experience and it's it
gets harder to do that as the realities
in the field of your experience become
more intense or
more unpredictable more frightening and
so this is where all the tricks we
learned from stoicism Buddhism and other
things to regulate into ground right
allows you to then experiment with other
practices like slowing down that's a
good one reflecting that's another good
one so yeah a lot of so that that was
not really a great answer if it was kind
of like rambling in the in the area
where you asked the question because I'm
not I can't give specific advice
everyone's in a very unique situation
you know the most general things you can
say are to take care of yourself and to
- yeah to take care of yourself and I'm
curious how you personally are taking
care of yourself interesting it's a
complicated question I mean I've been a
caregiver for many years like over a
decade so I was already in a routine of
having to step in to other people's pain
to be able to support them right and
then to not get so caught up in that
pain that then I destroy myself so I
already had some balance in that respect
psychologically but believe me it was
hard one so the basics you know eating
right trying to exercise and do a lot of
movement sleeping right I have a very
strict media diet which is to say I have
a limited amount of time that I look at
the media every day and that's important
so I get out of the infinite scroll the
infinite scroll is a hyper stimuli in a
technical evolutionary sense which is
that there was I don't know how big the
Library of Alexandria was but it was not
as big as ant-man so no matter how much
you wanted to scroll through the Library
of Alexandria so there's this sense of
just that is very disorienting
scroll and we have in all of a sudden
change to a social media environment
where they aren't banking money off of
us by selling us advertisements right
that hasn't happened like Facebook is
still basically incentivized to keep you
paying attention to sell your
advertisements sorry guys
so there's still a systemic disruption
of your infinite scroll in such a way as
to give you disorienting information so
you can't make a cohesive story and
leave time just so you know how it works
they studied the human nervous system to
dick people to Facebook to sell them
appetize months and we use Facebook like
we're saving the world with it so that's
the first step is unplug from that stuff
and plug into deeper long-form stuff and
specifically conversations people you
know all right we need to be together
with the people who we love and away
from the screens now sometimes we need
the screen to get us to that person that
we love but that's a different when
you're having 45 minutes zoom call with
somebody so I protect myself from
oversaturation of the media environment
we gen limited amount of time every day
and not simply not participating on
social media in the standard ways so
that's one good tip you know and then
you know beginning in those
conversations that I have with the
people that I love beginning the
beginning the difficult conversations
right having the difficult conversations
and there's many of those right money
right health death right these things
are now just like in the air and so the
degree to which you try to get along and
pretend like they're not makes it hard
we need to clear that space mm-hmm and
have a difficult conversation in a sense
before you have to write and then you
can create a safe container in which to
love one another and to deal with the
reality
and so again hard hard-won lessons from
difficult times but it's necessary the
difficult conversations happening you
need to trust yourself and the other
people that you can get through those
conversations so that's important and if
you need help having that conversation
seek help it's often hard to work that
stuff out one-on-one and there's
probably someone around you who loves
you who may be really skilled at that
right and there's going to be people
popping up trying to give these kinds of
supports all over the place I'm seeing
it happen I'm seeing like an emergent
pop up mental health safety net there's
a whole bunch of coaches and therapists
and other people and counselors trying
to find ways up and into people to get
them help specifically with these kinds
of dynamics so I kind of am of the
attitude of yeah you know kind of you
know embrace the suck right nothing at
Jamie real said that and be in the
tragedy the post tragic was in the
tragedy post tragic didn't find a way
out of the tragedy post tragic is right
in a burning in it burning in the
tragedy but not only the tragedy right
and so usually when you can have these
conversations and you can clear right
then you can touch transcendence without
denying the world and that's what needs
to happen that's that's those are the
liberating moments that you can find
even in pain and illness and sickness so
so that's some of what I'm doing is I'm
trying to have the conversations that
need to be had which is one of the
things we're being called to do you know
we're all working from home is this
notion of like we're supposed to be
having our old job from home but I
actually forgot to work that used to be
done in the home it's different nice if
it's the work of being in a home and
some of the most difficult work actually
which is why most people prefer to leave
the home and go work pretend like that's
the most important thing that the sand
castles were building right which are so
fragile as we're seeing these sand
castles
don't write or not as important as the
work we're doing right here every day
right around the table and so that's
where we're returning to and you know
many of us are fortunate enough to have
that table in a safe place but not
everyone has a table in the safe place
where they can have these conversations
so we need to put ourselves in context
get our shit together and then start
collaborating in a way that we've never
seen basically so that's the other thing
I'm trying to do I'm trying to as part
of my practice just work a little bit
harder and have more conversations than
I would normally have and kind of move
things forward in a in as Unseld finta
rest of the way as as possible in a way
where I'm basically trying to be what's
needed in the moment and again that's
focus ISM ride them trying to find a way
to clear what Zach might want and figure
out what the world needs and again
things hard hard thought hard one from
happy basically forced into being a
caregiver so for so many years myself
did you figure out out of me what the
moment needs and so this is it over or
call to do and then other things too
like once you clear the air and you're
in the tragedy but you're transcendent
but still minute right then you can
laugh again then you have post tragic
laughter you can have post tragic tears
that are not self-interested what was me
tears that are tears for the world right
and so there's a there's a humor
possible there's a levity that is
possible but it has to be the levity on
the other side of tragedy it can't be
the levity before we actually confront
it right so
I'll share having a very important
practice for me all these years was
watching America's money zone videos you
guys know America's find somebody yes
it's like the looks like very lowest
counted I'm they're like people falling
off the trampolines kind of stuff but I
just couldn't laugh it was so hard to
laugh sometimes because of what I was
dealing with and it's just like
someone's little banana peel you know
what I mean like so we need to remember
those things too and allow ourselves to
do that as well you know and so that's
important too which is once you're in it
and you admit that you're that and you
are dealing with it sentient but within
it then you can find love and laughter
and things even within tragedy and we
know this again from human experience in
history right that wars are terrible but
within the midst of war there is love
and even more intense and profound love
that happens in times of peace because
of what because of what demands of the
anima Mundi are making right the world
soul and transformation so yeah I said
yeah eat right gonna eat right yeah that
whole metaphor that really really landed
for me I like that a lot so let's open
it up to questions I'll unmute you when
I call your name
so Terry Patton um you had a couple of
things a couple questions I'm going to
unmute you so you can ask that to Zach
you know in in your essays Zach so much
sobriety and even in a kind of sternness
regarding the high probability of
personal moral failures in this war in
heaven between our better and darker
angels and I think implicit
there are some forms that this might
take that our most prominent when you
wrote the essay and your awareness and
also maybe least likely to be obvious to
others and I'd like to invite you to
reflect and elaborate hmm
right I mean in a sense I was writing to
several different kind of echelon right
some of what we're seeing at the highest
levels of decision-making is hard to
explain which is why we're getting so
much conspiracy theory right because
you're looking at the highest levels of
decision-making in political life not
just like in the last few weeks but like
for a couple decades and you're thinking
how did this how how did we get in the
situation these were human just making
choices over time and so when you think
about the war in heaven you're thinking
about what are the ideals that our
leaders have lived by that allowed a
society like this to exist when was the
choice made in their subjectivity to
align themselves with an ideal for
Humanity as opposed to another right so
one stratum writing to people was just
you know the power right and the
corruption of power and the fact that
now that the world has come on patterned
the possibility for power plays is
ridiculously big right so who is driving
which truck through this huge opening
into the future of infrastructure in
economics and mental health and
education and biometrics trying who's
driving through that and so part of me
is writing to that and saying like you
got the devil on your shoulder right but
there's an angel too and so at that
highest level there's this possibility
for either get off the stage if you
can't do the right thing
or realign yourself at a higher level
and then for the everyday right for the
salt of the earth this is about the
basic orientation of selfishness persons
care as far as I can see it right and
separation versus approach and so in a
sense I'm writing to all the people who
took way too much toilet paper right
it's like just check yourself right
because what happened is the imagination
opened up and all of the horrible
scenarios flooded in and they couldn't
control the most base instinct which is
self-protection
now why toilet paper I don't know I'm
not good enough psychologist right but
there's something about the root chakra
something about the root chakra and
something about this stuff we have in
our lives going on we don't want anyone
else to see which now may become
apparent because everything's being on
patterned right and so at the more base
level I'm just thinking about what world
do it because I'm not like a hyper agent
I'm not someone making massive decisions
affecting the future of infrastructure
and commodity supply chains and
healthcare but I am making decisions on
a day-to-day basis
right and it's the question of when am i
choosing out of a basic orientation of
separation and selfishness and what am i
choosing basically to lead with love and
care and concern and so far okay thank
God it's I've been able to make I feel
the right choice and I can go to bed at
night feeling good that I haven't become
someone worse as a result of being put
in a more difficult situation right and
so that's the basic request is that as a
situation gets more difficult can you
continue to be who you want to be can
you continue to be committed to the
things that allow you to be an interest
person and after a real someone
committed to your ideals
and so yeah so that's that's kind of
that's that knife edge basically and
that's the battle in heavens actually
this battle in the imaginal realms and
our own minds between different possible
selves right these different
trajectories of choice that's seen
people in difficult situations who get
in the kind of a choice cascade of bad
choices of a choice cascade of selfless
choices and then you end up the
situation becomes much worse than
already was because now you were like
overwhelmed by your own inability to be
the person you wanted to be in the
difficult situation and so there's just
this there's just a primacy on trying to
give people the capacity to be the
person that they did they want to be
visco so I'm trying to do in the whole
essay and so I didn't have particular I
mean bad actions are in mind it was just
that I've seen this choice point and
yeah and I but it's also that I think
the scales are tipped toward the light
if I can say that yeah and there's
there's a bunch of reasons to think that
but interesting research on both both
post-traumatic growth as a profound
possibility within humans and research
on what happens with people what happens
in natural disaster situations just
spontaneous emergence of care giver like
people who used to hate one another the
hurricane comes and now he's like
pulling the guy out of his house on the
raft kind of thing you don't even like
those words you see on the news of the
terrible horrible stories but most of
what happens behind the scenes in those
kind of events is people doing quite
extraordinary stuff and so the more of
that happens the more that's likely to
happen and so I'm imagining a grassroots
that's made of good choice making which
allows as the going gets tough to tip
the balance which is all I'm seeking as
while one would save the day because
we're in a tragedy but to tip the
balance so that in the long run a lot of
people can look back on what has
happened and be like whoa that was that
I am a better person for it even though
I may have suffered more than I thought
it was possible to suffer or been more
courageous than I thought it was I was
possible for me or or whatever right so
it's that moral fortitude how do we get
that in a post treated culture you don't
mind just a brief follow-up I'm quite
aware that I'm in relative comfort and
in this enforced retreat that gives me
space to be reflective but they didn't
future moments it'll perhaps be much
more binding and much more challenging
and so there's a kind of work in the
anticipation of a squeeze that might be
incumbent upon us right now and a kind
of as much as you know decades and
decades of spiritual practice in so many
different ways I've intended to dedicate
my life toward the good but this
interruption
asks for what ever I've known to be
recognized as provisional and something
more to be possible and so I can't take
for granted the wisdom I've already in
integrated as sufficient and so there is
an opportunity for
kind of not knowing and listening and
just openness of course but perhaps a
more radical kind of preparation and I'm
curious yeah I think it's good to be
thinking that way so people talk about
how like oh well there could be another
way of infections in the fall right
because this is how the 1918 pandemic
went right and so whether or not that's
true biologically there's certainly
truth to the fact that psychologically
this fall is going to be difficult right
that right now we are in anxious kind of
like shocked and like primed right and
losses happen about all kinds of loss
investments of time and energy and all
these things are now and so cost is
happening so you can look at the time
cycles of those things as a psychologist
you see that it takes time for those
kinds of events to sink in and things
and then there's a whole poem right
there's like it there's like a
depressive breakdown and so what we need
to do now is basically build networks of
connections social relationships which
is want to thank Ock the people you love
and expand that circle of people that
you love and the concreteness of both
conversations so that there is something
there to catch us all when when the
going gets hard or harder as you're
saying Terry and God let it not be the
case that it gets harder right like God
let us be overacting please but perf
let's prepare just in case and that
preparation would be to build those
networks to have those conversations and
to you know be conscious like be
explicit like hey we're connecting now
and it could get harder and I'll be
there for you and you'll be there for me
and those things those conversations
matter more now than they ever did and
knowing that you've got to couple people
right three or four people maybe if
you're lucky about more right
we'll be there and to talk to you like
that's so important so the main thing is
not to me like some fancy meditation
practice or some fancy prayer practice
or anything like it's not that it's
actually something about community and
relationship and those conversations
that get us in touch with the other
realities that are here on earth right
or two realities of love and realities
of vision and imagination right and and
so to just see those we have to be
together and we have to start getting
comfortable being more or intimate even
though we're in fact physically
distanced so that would be my my prepper
God would be you know I'm not like a
prepper like stockpile food and all that
stuff I'm like that's not really gonna
matter right if you don't have community
and relationship and the ability to be
with people there's no escape hatch
right and this is this is a shout out to
like the really wealthy people there's
no escape match right there's actually
no place you can bug out right every
sketch at escape hatch goes deeper in to
some kind of intensity of relationship
and culture right so so just we have to
realize that we're in it all together
and so yeah you know go out stand ten
feet away and talk to your neighbor
right to figure out who's around and
that would be my recommendation as far
as preparing for the emotional for the
emotional kind of journey that were
headed for Thank You Terry it's good to
see you there so I'm going to call on
Ashley Ashley I will unmute you hello so
I am an educator and I was wondering
what are some what are some actionable
steps I can take in bringing my students
up to speed
but moreover I I have connections with
our local mayor and so the other day I
was thinking like I used to have a
conversation with the mayor what does
that conversation look like in this time
and space without turning him off - the
transitions that I see forming and at
the opportune time to have those
conversations mm-hmm
interesting I mean as an educator as
well I'm somewhat biased but I think the
conversation with the mayor is the
conversation about the kids right like
because other people having
conversations with the mayor about like
testing and quarantine procedure and
hand-washing and all that stuff right
but for me as a psychologist educator
again the main event is what's happening
right now to the kids like everyone's
affected but there are certain
developmental transitions particularly
adolescents where this is like a not
great to be in that lesson right now
like it's like it's terrible to be a
vulnerable old person this is correct
but from an identity formation
perspective front right the people who
are forming their adult identities now
under these life conditions are the
leaders of the future and will determine
what happens ten years from them right
right and it may be given the history of
civil unrest globally they may be
determining what happens just a few
months from now right we have to look at
Maoism and Nazism and you look at the
growth of massive civil unrest movements
when you're looking at disenfranchised
adolescent or early adult males and so
there's a huge need to focus on creating
resources and opportunities for
adolescents to do work that's not rote
being a school work that is work that
makes them feel like they're
contributing to their communities so
like interview projects with teams of
adolescents and old people
have stories to share like is huge I
think those forms of intergenerational
transmission other things that
adolescents can do to feel like they're
creative right co-creating videos that
talk to their experience or I'm just
saying we can't be thinking about how to
get these kids prepared for college all
right that's not now it's all the time
for that now it's the time to help them
through the coming months and to give
them and to give them tools that will be
empowering them especially in terms of
their identities and and also to just
not make them feel invisible because
right now I think there are many
populations in the fact that feel
completely invisible who are very very
vulnerable but not in the ways that
people think and I could speak into that
but I'm speaking to adolescents now
because the media focuses on this one
thing it's as if nothing else is I think
but there's a lot of other stuff
happening in someone what's happening is
you know millions and millions of
adolescents cut off from their friends
at a time when developmentally is
precisely when they should be out of the
house
hanging with their friends right not for
having fun but for having the necessary
differentiation from the parental
holding container to have an autonomous
identity and all that stuff right so
yeah so that's a little bit of it I
would talk to the mayor about something
like that like we've got an act we
already had an adolescent mental health
crisis right and then this happened what
can we do to actually somehow seize the
moment
and yeah and I think it's actually it's
critical for for the future that this
affect the youth in a net positive way
which is best to say that it's an
opportunity for maturation which creates
a generation that's very powerful as
opposed to something that's very
debilitating so that that's where I'm
I'm thinking in those in those areas can
I follow up totally if you were talking
about boots on the ground so if the
one topic I mean it could be identity
development I work with both high
schoolers but I'm also adjunct college
so if we're talking boots on the ground
I feel like there is this spiritual
pigness right in our society and and
it's this taboo space to to access with
these younger generations because
there's no grounding as a society right
now is is there a topic that would that
could that you think would resonate with
them to be a springboard for them to
understand the power that they have and
you know where to go with that power
from here forward I mean I I keep
returning to that the kids need to learn
history from their elders I keep
returning to that because really the key
to them actualizing their historical
agency as a generation and as
individuals is by knowing where they are
in his dream and and so especially the
stories from elders that are about time
that were fundamentally different than
the times now right they're actually in
a way normalize these times because we
realize that whoa you know other
generations have had abrupt world
historical significant events occur and
so yeah I think if we could get them to
engage in a form of intergenerational
kind of conversation and let them steer
like let them ask the questions to the
elders that they want to ask it's our
responsibility to get that container
created and to make it appealing and
valued by the society that this is as
important or more important than your
schoolwork right to have every day in
our long conversation with son of an
older person from the community you've
never met right and you run through your
series of questions and you start to get
this like
panorama of all these different lives
and all these different time periods
right and so that I think is some of it
and other forms of creativity you know
with digital cameras and recording
equipment and a bunch of stuff there is
the possibility for capturing their
first-person experiences basically
artistically and creating something like
a museum of adolescence and childhood
artistic expressions of dealing with the
crisis basically so like a collaborative
art project among hundreds of groups of
adolescents or something like that
and I'm just completely spitballing I
haven't thought it through but my hope
is that and I'm sure there are people
trying to think about this stuff you
know and so it got to be to the people
to me that work a success story I love
that because backlog talks about shadow
boxes and time and space and
understanding how even in organic
objects are meaningful so I love it
thank you very much for the feedback
okay all right Amy you had a question
I will unmute you so I am also I'm also
an educator and I you had mentioned this
the concept of the one-room schoolhouse
in your essay a bit and I was wondering
what what your kind of vision of the
one-room schoolhouse of the future is
and if this could analog or scale to
adults unlike a one-room schoolhouse
working situation
interesting yeah I in my book education
and a time between worlds I lay out in
some detail this vision of what I call
an educational hub Network and what it
is it's it's basically a base you could
take an existing school system and
you've got all the school buildings so
you change the architecture of the
school buildings to make those buildings
something more like a community center
slash co-working space slash library
slash museum in that place you have a
bunch of Technology and a bunch of
teacher citizen scientists who basically
facilitate the creation of pop-up
classrooms that also implicate the
parents in the community so next to the
education that Network there's a whole
bunch of social miracles including basic
income guarantee which basically allows
parents the freedom to re-engage in
their own education specifically
targeted towards being able to help
their children in this education hub
network so the backend technology is
something like a time and skill sharing
and content delivery system which houses
you know all the skills and curricula
within the community and that includes
not just the official teachers but also
the parents and professionals in the
community who want to be part of that so
this is if those of you who've read Ivan
Illich D schooling Society this is like
a version of that so the one-room
schoolhouse is actually everywhere
around that hub there are all of these
classrooms popping up where let's say a
student who wants to study a particular
historical time period finds several
other students who want to store it and
study that time period at different ages
they find two adults who have a
knowledge and a location in the city
where that time period is relevant right
and then for three hours that location
in the city becomes a classroom where
kids of different ages are interacting
around the historical event with the
guidance of let's say someone paid by
the state to be there and to parents who
are you
or an old person who was actually there
at the time that it happened there so
that that's the vision it's a it's a
very decentralized way of thinking about
having an educational network structure
a lot hinges upon the technological back
end which is what coordinates to pop-up
classrooms and actually houses all the
student work and creates a kind of
self-organizing assessment system so
that we and it ends up being quite a
complicated technological problem as
well as far as getting that many
students into that much diverse activity
and still a sharing educational equity
and still assuring the basic acquisition
of things like reading writing and so
there's more typical that's that's kind
of the basic vision and right now in
some place that's but certainly not in
all places you're having little visions
of this where school has now all the
sudden had to run like a spoken-- hub
model it's had to run all these little
classrooms in every living room in town
right and we're trying to do that but
there's some there's so much variability
in how well that's that's being done
right now but we're becoming aware that
this is this is a modality of Education
that the digital affords cool so we may
have time for one or two questions Alex
s and went unmute you if you can ask
your question thanks Peter okay great
thanks Zack for coming out and joining
us in the forum so I'm finding your
presentation really interesting at a
number of level but the thing I was
wondering about it kind of actually
piggy backs on a question I think it was
Nikolas blasted it was one of the first
ones and it had to do with the mythical
poetic side of things that's the that's
the word that he used and I was
wondering so to me it seems like you
know when thinking about this crisis
these
skilled events that are going on there
can be two approaches they're sort of a
right hand and a left hand
maybe so there is the the the kind of
rational scientific philosophical
approach and I guess I see stoicism as
an example by the Stoics were very
logical you know they were all about
reason but also reason as virtue right
not just like narrow self-interest but
still like they were all about logic and
and and reason in that sense and then
you have the kind of more mythical side
on the other hand that seems to be more
about emotion
if the Stoics are all about harmony here
there's a synthesis on struggle right
conflict and you talk about you know the
end of things
in your article and so I'm wondering
like how you see you mention you talk
about reason there as well
in your in your piece and I'm just
wondering how you see those two
interacting is one more important than
the other you know how do they come
together interesting yeah I mean so
you're setting up like the two I would
actually say that there's three because
you have the kind of rational scientific
let's say at the mythopoetic and I think
you have the artistic or subjective
which is which is getting at a different
thing and my sense is that and I try to
get at this in the in the article which
is that none of those alone are
sufficient and each of those need one
another that the ration all ends up if
you're follow it through like the Stoics
did the rational ends up pointing beyond
itself right but the mythic ends up also
being incomplete right because it asks
questions of the world which we can act
on and get answers about
and then of course the artistic requires
those other two as input that the
artistic can't stand alone it actually
has to do with some take on the nature
of the world and some take on what it
means and then you're putting it out
individually with an aesthetic
presentation so I'm seeing like a
complex kind of relationship between all
three of those where I wouldn't say one
is primary but that they're in some kind
of moving dance some kind of evolving
dance and so what I'm asking people who
are oriented to the spiritual and the
mythological to do is in the sense start
becoming more rational and when I'm in
the paper anyway and when I'm what I'm
asking the people who are orienting just
as scientists to do is to say hey admit
the fact that the thoughts of the heart
matter and the paper itself is more like
something I'm singing right because I'm
not really arguing anything and I'm not
citing any facts I'm just expressing
myself basically so the paper is in fact
making almost the aesthetic validity
claim more than anything else but
there's a harmony to the aesthetic right
and there's a truthfulness that's
expressed in those so I'm so I'm seeing
yeah I guess I'm saying it's it's not
the one or the other it's actually this
much more complex that's not even - I
like to go because I'm saying three this
is me actually rooting into landries
metaphysics for orientation for those of
you who are into the footnotes so that's
kind of how I'm seeing it and in the
paper like I said I'm trying to just
strike a balance that's not really
between all all three great well squeeze
in one more question
Nicholas would you like to ask your
question if you can put yourself off
mute so thank you sac for being here
[Music]
yeah so I just wanted to sort of ask
DOMA is really like a space that is so
foreign from my everyday life right like
the conversations we're having here are
just so like they make sense the people
that partake in these in the space
but if you try and you know get to these
difficult conversations that you were
mentioning I was yeah so you sort of
really elaborated on the role of
language but how how does this language
have to evolve in order all right people
to sort of understand and and to help
them with the transition to the to the
new world right there because we're in
the in between these two worlds like you
said so I want to keep it short so you
can maybe still quickly answer it I
think you right totally that's I mean
this is actually a great question this
is the question that the therapist and
the educator and the parent needs to ask
right which is it's not like how do i
beam you to the top of the mountain so
you can see the view it's like if I beam
you to the top like teleport you to the
top of the mountain you'll be
disoriented and confused maybe you'll be
excited and you'll see some stuff but
then when you go back down you won't
remember how you got there or what
happened so the what you need to do is
figure out that path up the mountain and
it will take time
but it's one of the kind of crisis
moments as that in fact everyone's being
asked right now to be some kind of
philosopher or saint like everyone has
to like stay home behave right face
death worried like and like and like
handle their shit like and still like
work and take care of the kids and stuff
it's like whoa everyone is being beamed
at the top of a stoic mountain to try to
remain calm and find harmony in the
midst of chaos so that means for those
of us who by whatever means or fate
ended up climbing quite a distance
before this happened there is some
obligation to try to find a way not to
like just drop it all on the table at
once but mm you know like that's the
worst pedagogical advice you need to
find the ways in right both the moments
in the conversation and those topics
that are naturally philosophical right
now good teachers can kind of recognize
like oh that's like a vein that we can
get in kind of open up because you're
already interested in it right you're
not afraid to go there
so like yeah so that's basically kind of
a teacher late advice to say be a
careful enough conversation partner to
kind of to follow their lead like that's
what pedagogy means it means to lead
along so but first you need to see kind
of where they're going in the sense like
it needs a need to detect it and be
careful and then know when you're
pushing too far right no when they can't
handle it anymore
and yeah so I think but just to ask the
question is a student right because many
people who operate philosophically or
just tracking more they'll just dump it
on people even when people can't handle
it don't want to handle it don't want to
think about it right so I'm careful like
this with my own family it's like just
little droplets of stuff that I'm seeing
not the whole deluge which would send
him into a panic attack something right
so you just needs to be this care even
in conversation and you're caring for
their better self right so it's not like
what's ken wilber just called idiot
compassion idiot compassion is when you
let the alcoholic stay in alcoholic cuz
you're just being nice because you don't
want to make him feel bad that's not
what we're doing this is a subtle
balance between challenge and support
essentially with a clear and explicit
sense of like I love you no matter what
even if you never come to grips with it
so there also has to be that sense of
like people can learn and change and
transform people can even roll over
their identity if they're held in a safe
container so often what I do before
these conversations is have other
conversations that makes it clear that
we're friends it's safe you know like we
can still be together
I don't need you to understand me or
follow me here
for me to respect you and love you right
so give that containment and support and
then challenge
and deepen and contextualise and all of
those things that you want to do to
bring people out of a narrower view so
but good it's the right question to ask
and that's an amazing answer so thank
you so much great so we'll close up in
the in a moment but I just like to hand
it to Zack for any kind of closing
thoughts this was wonderful for me I
like I said I hadn't talked to like a
classroom of people in awhile and so it
was really nice to see all your faces
and to get the different questions from
people in different places and yeah so I
you know I feel better now that I did
when I started to call so this is
improving my own point which is that
just talking with people in a long form
and being together is very it's
important for us and so yeah so just
thank you guys and keep up your good
work and keeps us going and let me know
if I can you know kind of help anyone in
any way you you can find my email
through my website or Peter can give it
to you so please reach out if there's
something I can do great great and I'll
make some closing announcements for
upcoming events in a moment but Zack
thank you so much for coming to the
stolid today was a wonderful experience
Hey all right so I'll take off see you
guys stay hit take care
so for upcoming events I'll announce
next three we have a Adam Robert coming
in at 6:00 p.m. Eastern time and
philosophy the practice of death and
dying as Plato famously said you know
the philosophy true philosophy is the
practice of death and dying so this we
had talked in a Q&A similar to this and
then at 7:30 right after that we're
gonna have an existential dance party
with Colin Morris from the Zion 2.0
podcast it should be a treat last week
was really really fun
and then tomorrow at 12 p.m. Eastern
Time Richard Bartlett's coming in for
experimental exercise called alongside
miss
and how he described it is you know we
saw kind of fixated on our vision that
sometimes we just need to pause and look
beside us and see who is alongside us so
we designed some interesting
conversational techniques to be
compatible with zoom so you can RSVP all
that - all that on the website sign up
for the mailing list and I'm viewing the
stoah as a gift to everyone to freely
use and this time of need and if you're
inspired to provide a gift to the stoah
feel free to go on the website and at
the bottom there's more information that
the gift economy section alright so
thank you so much everyone for coming
out and with the excellent questions
today that was awesome
[Music]